Register of the Dmitriĭ Aleksandrovich Levchik papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dmitriĭ Aleksandrovich Levchik papers
1985-2004
2001C1
Hoover Institution Archives
27 manuscript boxes (11.2 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes, election campaign literature, and other printed matter relating to political conditions and election campaigns in Russia, activities of the Sot͡sial-demokraticheskai͡a Partii͡a Rossiĭskoĭ Federat͡sii, and organization of independent miners' trade unions in Russia.
Levchik, Dmitrii Aleksandrovich.
Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at https://searchworks.stanford.edu. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Dmitriĭ Aleksandrovich Levchik, a Russian political analyst and consultant based in Moscow, was involved in establishing independent trade unions and independent political and trade union publications during and immediately after the collapse of the Soviet system.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Dmitriĭ Aleksandrovich Levchik consist of writings, correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes, election campaign literature, and other printed matter relating to political conditions and election campaigns in Russia, activities of the Sot͡sial-demokraticheskai͡a Partii͡a Rossiĭskoĭ Federat͡sii, and organization of independent miners' trade unions in Russia.
An increment acquired in 2013 contains communist political materials concerning post-1991 election campaigns and the political activities of leftist groups in the Russian Federation. Particularly notable are letters to the editor of Pravda from the mid-1990s. Ranging from requests for information on the condition of Lenin's mausoleum and its security to proposals for breathing new life into the communist idea, these letters, which came from throughout the former USSR and as far away as Greece, illustrate the worldviews of communist believers whose dreams were punctured by the collapse of the USSR.
The original folder titles given by the creator have been maintained. Within individual folders, materials have been kept in their original order as accumulated by the creator.
Nezavisim'yi profsoiuz gorniakov Rossii.; Sotsial-demokraticheskaia partiia Rossiiskoi Federatsii.; Elections--Russia (Federation); Labor unions--Russia (Federation); Miners--Russia (Federation); Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-; Socialism--Russia (Federation)
- Subject File, 1987-2004
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains reports, memoranda, notes, election campaign literature, and other printed matter relating to political conditions and election campaigns in Russia, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Deputatskie materialy, 1991-1993
    - Delo deputata A. Kalinina, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - Krasnogvardeiskii raisovet Moskvy, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 25, Box-folder 8: 1-3)
    - Taking Charge (Association of State Democratic Chairs), circa 1993 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Izbiratel'nye bloki i partii, 1990-2004
    - Agrarnaia partiia Rossii, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Assotsiatsiia oblastei i gorodov Tsentral'nogo raiona Rossii, 1992 (Box-folder 7: 21)
    - Assotsiatsiia sotsial'no-politicheskikh ekspertov i konsul'tantov, 1995 (Box-folder 7: 14)
    - Bratstvo kandidatov v nastoiashchie liudi, 1995 (Box-folder 7: 15)
    - Derzhava, 1995 (Box-folder 5: 5-6)
    - Dvizhenie Soiuz internatsionalistov, 1994 (Box-folder 26: 11)
    - Dvizhenie Za spravedlivost', 1992-1993 (Box-folder 7: 22)
    - Federal'naia partiia Svobodnaia Rossiia, 1999 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Grazhdanskii soiuz, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Gruppa Svobodnye vybory, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 19)
    - Iabloko-blok Iavlinskogo, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Kommunisticheskaia partiia Rossiiskoi Federatsii (KPRF), 1993-2003 (Box-folder 27: 12, Box-folder 7: 7)
    - KPRF- Mezhnatsional'nyi soiuz (Kampaniia Aleksandra Zaitseva), 1995 (Box-folder 6: 9-10)
    - Liberal'no-demokraticheskaia partiia Rossii (LDPR), 1993 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - Mezhregional'nye assotsiatsii, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 23)
    - Molodaia Rossiia, 1992 (Box-folder 7: 16)
    - Moskovskii tsentr bol'shevistskoi platformy v KPSS, 1991 (Box-folder 26: 12)
    - Narodnaia partiia gorniakov Rossii (Otdel mezhdunarodnykh sviazei i obshchestvennykh otnoshenii), 1991-1995
      - Arkhiv NPGR (Narodnaia partiia gorniakov Rossii) and NGPU (Narodnaia partiia gorniakov Ukrainy), 1992 (Box-folder 3: 7)
      - Correspondence, statements, resolutions, and reports, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3: 1-4, Box-folder 2: 14-15)
      - Evropa, Avstraliia, blizhnee zarubezh'e, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 5)
      - Ob"edinenie Shakhtery Rossii, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4: 10-11)
      - Ob"edinennyi zabastkom Severoural'ska i NPG Severoural'ska, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3: 12-14, Box-folder 4: 1-8)
        Correspondence, appeals, statements, memoranda, and press releases.
      - Sotsiologicheskie oprosy, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 8-9)
      - Sviazi s SSHA, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Narodnyi al'ians, 1994 (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - Nash dom-Rossiia, 1995 (Box-folder 5: 10-11)
    - Nash vybor (Kampaniia Vladislava Gus'kova), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 6: 7-8)
    - Nezavisimaia partiia (nezavisimye kandidaty), 1993 (Box-folder 7: 24)
    - Obshcherossiiskaia politicheskaia obshchestvennaia organizatsiia Otechestvo, 2000 (Box-folder 24: 19)
    - Obshchestvennaia koalitsiia Grazhdanskoe obshchestvo, 1999 (Box-folder 11: 13)
    - Obshchestvennaia organizatsiia invalidov Chernobylia, 2001 (Box-folder 27: 14)
    - Obshchie svedeniia, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 5: 8-9)
    - Ob"edinennye demokraticheskie levye, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 20)
    - Ob"edinennye sotsial-demokraty, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - Oppozitsiia, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 6: 3-4)
    - Otdel'nye kandidaty (108 okrug), 1995 (Box-folder 6: 11-13)
    - Partiia Rossiiskogo edinstva i soglasiia, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Partiia trudiashchikhsia, 2004 (Box-folder 26: 14)
    - Prokommunisticheskie organizatsii, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 26: 13)
    - Rossiiskaia partiia budushchego, 2000 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Rossiiskii obshchenarodnyi soiuz i Derzhavnaia partiia, 1994 (Box-folder 24: 16)
    - Rossiiskoe dvizhenie demokraticheskikh reform, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Russkoe natsional'noe edinstvo, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
    - Soglasiie vo imia Rossii, 1995 (Box-folder 7: 12)
    - Soiuz aktsionerov MMM, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - Soiuz nezavisimykh, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 17)
    - Sotsial-demokraticheskaia partiia Rossiiskoi Federatsii (SDPR), 1990-2001 (Box-folder 17: 7, Box-folder 1: 1-5)
      Minutes of meetings, resolutions, statements, appeals, stenographic records, and press reviews.
      - II s"ezd, 1990 (Box-folder 21: 11)
      - III s"ezd, 1990 (Box-folder 21: 12)
      - IV s"ezd, 1992 (Box-folder 21: 20)
      - V s"ezd, 1993 (Box-folder 1: 6-7)
        Includes questionnaires of congress delegates.
      - Arkhiv gazety Novaia sotsial-demokratiia, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 7)
      - Finansovo-khoziaistvennaia deiatel'nost', 1991 (Box-folder 22: 2)
      - Materialy plenumov, 1991 (Box-folder 21: 18)
      - Materialy pravleniia, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 21: 13-15)
      - Moskovskaia oblastnaia organizatsiia SDPR, 1991-1999 (Box-folder 21: 19)
      - Partiinoe stroitel'stvo, 1990-2001 (Box-folder 21: 8-9, Box-folder 24: 11-12)
      - Rossiiskie gorodskie organizatsii SDPR, 1993 (Box-folder 24: 9-10)
      - Sluzhba izbiratel'nykh kampanii SDPR, 1991-1993
        - Manuals, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 1: 8)
        - Questionnaires of congress delegates, 1993 (Box-folder 1: 9-12)
        - Reports, memoranda, manuals, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1: 13-14, Box-folder 2: 1-2)
      - "Sotsial-demokratiia v posttotalitarnom obshchestve," conference, 1992 (Box-folder 22: 1)
      - Uchreditel'nyi s"ezd, 1990 (Box-folder 21: 10)
    - Sotsial'nyi soiuz Rossii (proekt), 1995 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    - Strategiia i taktika arkhivov Rossiiskikh politicheskikh partii, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 19)
      Includes typescript by Levchik.
    - Vybor Rossii, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Kampaniia po otzyvu M. L. Zakharova, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Khartiia-93, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Kommunisticheskaia agitatsiia v armii, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 26: 10)
  - Kommunisticheskii samizdat, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 27: 8-9)
  - Konferentsiia gorodskogo deputatskogo korpusa Moskvy, 1991 (Box-folder 24: 15)
  - Kontent-analiz moskovskoi pressy, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 3-6)
  - Koordinatsionnyi tsentr Chestnye vybory, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 12: 8-11)
  - Martovsko-aprel'skii krizis vlasti, 1992-1993
    - Arkhiv gazety Brateevo, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 8: 11-13)
    - Arkhiv gazety Za Moskva-reko i, Nos. 1-10, 1992 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - Referendum doveriia vlasti, 1993 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Seminar aktiva Partii ekonomicheskoi svobody, 1993 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Sentiabr'skie sobytiia, 1993 September 21 - October 4 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Moskovskii orgkomitet po podgotovke Grazhdanskogo foruma, 2001 (Box-folder 16: 14: 15)
  - Politicheskie dvizheniia, 1994-2001
    - Antikolonial'naia liga, 1996 (Box-folder 26: 15)
    - Levye, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 16: 13-14)
    - Natsionalisty, 2001 (Box-folder 16: 12)
  - Politicheskie neformal'nye gruppy, 1987-2000
    - Mezhprofessional'nyi klub Demokraticheskaia perestroika, 1987-1992
      - Federatsiia sotsialisticheskikh obshchestvennykh klubov, 1988 (Box-folder 18: 4)
      - Litovskoe dvizhenie za perestroiku, 1989 (Box-folder 19: 2)
      - Neformal'nye zhurnaly "Merkurii," "V polnyi rost," "Demokrat" (neopublikovannye), 1987-1988 (Box-folder 19: 12, Box-folder 18: 1-2)
      - Materialy diskussii, 1988 (Box-folder 17: 5)
      - Materialy mezhgorodskogo rabochego soveshchaniia demokraticheskikh klubov sotsial'nogo naznacheniia, 1989 (Box-folder 19: 9)
      - Mezhdunarodnaia deiatel'nost', 1988 (Box-folder 17: 6)
      - Mezhklubnaia partiinaia gruppa KPSS, 1988 (Box-folder 18: 6)
      - Mezhklubnyi informtsentr (protokoly), 1987-1988 (Box-folder 17: 9)
      - Moskovskii narodnyi front, 1988 (Box-folder 18: 3)
      - Moskovskii partiinyi klub Kommunisty za perestroiku, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 19: 10, Box-folder 18: 7-13)
      - Otkrytaia zona, informatsionno-diskussionnyi biulleten', 1988 (Box-folder 19: 13)
      - Seminar Modeli sotsializma, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 19: 1, Box-folder 18: 5, Box-folder 17: 4)
      - Sotsial'no-politicheskii klub, 1987 (Box-folder 17: 9)
      - Ustav, spiski chlenov, protokoly sobranii, konferentsii, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 17: 1-3, Box-folder 19: 3-8, Box-folder 17: 10-13)
    - Molodezhnyi tsentr po pravam cheloveka Barrikada, 1992 (Box-folder 24: 14)
    - Ob"edinennye demokraticheskie levye, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Ob"edinennye sotsial-demokraty, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 9-10)
    - Politicheskie neformal'nye gruppy Sevastopol'skogo raiona Moskvy, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 17: 8)
    - Rossiiskii narodnyi front, 1989 (Box-folder 19: 11)
    - Rossiiskie uchenye sotsialisticheskoi orientatsii (RUSO), 1997-2000 (Box-folder 27: 1-3)
      Includes conference speeches.
    - Sotsial-demokraticheskaia assambleia, 1991 (Box-folder 21: 7)
    - Sotsial-demokraticheskaia assotsiatsiia (SDA), 1989-1991
      - Assambleia SDA, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 9)
      - Finansovo-khoziaistvennaia deiatel'nost', 1990-1991 (Box-folder 21: 4, Box-folder 20: 7)
      - Informatsionnaia set' i vybory, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 2)
      - Informatsionnyi tsentr Novyi povorot, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 8)
      - Ispolnitel'nyi komitet, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 4)
      - Mezhdunarodnaia SDA, 1990 (Box-folder 21: 5-6)
      - Mezhdunarodnye sviazi, 1989 (Box-folder 21: 1-3, Box-folder 20: 1)
      - Personal'noe chlenstvo, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 5)
      - Plenumy soveta, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 6)
      - SDA Rossii, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 16-20)
      - SDA Srednei Azii, 1989-1990
        - Kazakhstan, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 10)
        - Kirgiziia, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 11)
        - Tadzhikistan, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 20: 13)
        - Uzbekistan, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 12)
      - SDA Ukrainy, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 20: 14-15)
      - Uchreditel'nyi s"ezd, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 20: 3)
    - Sovety obshchezhitii Sankt-Peterburga, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Profsoiuznoe dvizhenie v Rossii, 1990-2001
    - Konfederatsiia truda Rossii, 1995 (Box-folder 24: 18)
    - Obshchie svedeniia, 1990-2001 (Box-folder 23: 10-13)
  - Rabochee dvizheniie (neprofsoiuznoe) i inye profsoiuzy (ne shakhterskie), 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3: 10-11)
  - Territorial'noe obshchestvennoe samoupravlenie (TOS), 1989-2002
    - Komitety obshchestvennogo samoupravleniia v Rossii, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 16: 8-11)
    - Mestnoe samoupravlenie-mekhanizm realizatsii konstitutsionnosti Rossii, nauchno-prakticheskaia konferentsiia, 2002 (Box-folder 21: 17)
    - Mestnoe samoupravlenie, Moskovskaia oblast', 1989-2000 (Box-folder 23: 1-4, Box-folder 8: 6, Box-folder 21: 16)
    - Obshchie svedeniia, 2001 (Box-folder 16: 7)
    - Rossiiskaia assotsiatsiia organov territorial'nogo obshchestvennogo samoupravleniia, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 24: 17)
    - Rossiiskoe ob"edinenie sil samoupravleniia, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 23: 5-7)
  - Vybory i dovybory v mestnye sovety, 1989-2001
    - Belgorodskaia oblast', 2001 (Box-folder 24: 8)
    - Moskovskaia oblast', 1996-1999
      - Brateevo, Tushino, Mytishchi, 1999 (Box-folder 11: 9-12)
      - Kampaniia Olega Sotnikova, 1998 (Box-folder 10: 3)
      - Liubertsy, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 15: 1-5)
      - Obshchie svedeniia, 1996 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    - Otechestvo (Velikhov, Shokhin, Luzhkov), 1999 (Box-folder 12: 5-7)
    - Rossiskaia partiia zashchity zhenshchin, 1999 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Soiuz pravykh sil (A. E. Gerber), 1999 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - Vybory glav administratsii, 1998-2001
      - Karachaevo-Cherkessiia, 1999 (Box-folder 27: 10)
      - Komi SSR, 2001 (Box-folder 22: 3)
      - Riazanskaia oblast', 2000
        - Bulaev, Nikolai (Box-folder 14: 5)
        - Diagrammy parnogo raspredeleniia pokazatelei po sel'skim raionam Riazanskoi oblasti (Box-folder 14: 6-7)
        - Frolov, Sergei (Box-folder 14: 2)
        - Kanaev, Leonid (Box-folder 14: 3)
        - Liubimov, Viacheslav (Box-folder 14: 1)
        - Malakhov, Mikhail (Box-folder 13: 12)
        - Markov, Vladimir (Box-folder 13: 11)
        - Milekhin, Viktor (Box-folder 14: 4)
        - Predlozheniia po izbiratel'noi kampanii, 2000 (Box-folder 13: 7-8)
        - Riumin, Valerii (Box-folder 13: 9-10, Box-folder 14: 8-14)
      - Sotsial'no-politicheskoe razvitie regiona v kontse XX veka, by issledovatel'skaia gruppa "Nauka i proizvodstvo,", 2000 (Box-folder 13: 6)
      - Volgograd, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 9: 13-14, Box-folder 10: 1-2)
    - Vybory gubernatorov, 1994-2001
      - Irkutskaia oblast', 2001
        - Balashov, Aleksandr (Box-folder 16: 3)
        - Drobysheva, Liudmila (Box-folder 16: 4)
        - Govorin, Boris (Box-folder 16: 2)
        - Levchenko, Sergei (Box-folder 16: 1)
        - Mezhevich, Valentin (Box-folder 16: 5)
        - Sakharov, Sergei (Box-folder 16: 6)
      - Krasnoiarskii krai, 1994-1999
        - Blok Golos Rossii, 1998 (Box-folder 11: 7-8)
        - Ekonomicheskoe dvizhenie Kedr, 1994-1999 (Box-folder 11: 5-6)
        - Izbiratel'nyi blok Soiuz dela i poriadka, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 11: 3)
        - Lebed', Aleksandr, 1998 (Box-folder 11: 2)
        - Vtoroi tur, 1998 (Box-folder 11: 4)
        - Zubov, Valerii, 1998 (Box-folder 11: 1, Box-folder 10: 4-13)
      - Lipetskaia oblast', 2001 (Box-folder 27: 11)
      - Obshchie svedeniia, 1997 (Box-folder 9: 3-4)
    - Vybory narodnykh deputatov RSFSR i gorsoveta, Komi SSR, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 5: 1-4, Box-folder 4: 11-13)
      - Dela 1-6, 8, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4: 11-13, Box-folder 5: 1-4)
      - Protokoly zasedanii Soveta Vorkutinskoi federatsii nezavisimogo profsoiuza rabotnikov ugol'noi promyshlennosti, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 6)
      - Zakony respubliki Komi o vyborakh, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Vybory prezidenta Chuvashskoi respubliki (Nikolai Fedorov), 1998-2001 (Box-folder 23: 8-9, Box-folder 13: 2-5)
  - Vybory prezidenta Rossii, 2000 (Box-folder 27: 13)
  - Vybory v Moskovskuiu gosudarstvennuiu dumu, 1993-2003
    - Gruzdev, Vladimir, 2000 (Box-folder 15: 10)
    - Korablin, Iurii, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - Kuz'min, Vitalii, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 1)
    - Levchenko, Aleksandr, 2001 (Box-folder 15: 8)
    - Obshchie materialy po vyboram, 1993-2003 (Box-folder 9: 5-12, Box-folder 15: 6-7, Box-folder 24: 2, Box-folder 27: 4-7, Box-folder 22: 4-7)
    - Pomazanov, Vladimir, 2001 (Box-folder 22: 12)
    - Shakirov, Rim, 2001 (Box-folder 22: 10)
    - Shakkum, Martin, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 7)
    - Sergeeva, Ol'ga, 2001 (Box-folder 22: 11)
    - Stebenkova, Liudmila, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 15: 9)
    - Vakhaniia, Vladimir, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 6)
    - Vasil'ev, Mark, 2001 (Box-folder 15: 11-13, Box-folder 22: 8-9)
    - Zaporozhets, Aleksandr, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 5)
  - Vybory v Udmurtii (V. Lialin), 1995
  - Vystuplenie Pervogo sekretaria MGK KPSS tov. El'tsina B. N. na vstreche s propagandistkim arkhivom g. Moskvy 11 aprelia 1986 g. (Box-folder 24: 13)
  - Ustav goroda Moskvy, Moskovskii gorodskoi sovet narodnykh deputatov, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Zakony o politicheskikh partiiakh, 1995 (Box-folder 5: 7)
- Correspondence, 1985-1998
  Consists of letters from individuals and organizations in response to publications in the Pravda newspaper and the Kommunist magazine. Includes clippings and writings. Arranged chronologically.
  - Former Soviet Republics: Belarus, Kazkhstan, Moldova, and Ukraine, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 26: 8-9)
  - Greece, 1985 (Box-folder 26: 10)
  - Russia, 1991-1998
    - 1991 (Box-folder 25: 1)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 25: 2-3)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 25: 4-11)
    - 1994 (Box-folder 25: 12-15)
    - 1995 (Box-folder 26: 1-2, Box-folder 25: 14-15)
    - 1996 (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 26: 4-5)
    - 1998 (Box-folder 26: 6)